这会成为数十亿人都想使用的东西。
This is gonna be a thing that billions of people want to use.
构建东西对你来说是什么感觉？
What does building things feel like to you?
永生有可能实现吗？
Is living forever a possibility?
好，那如果带我进入你的脑海里，然后快进到 2030 年，
Okay, so like if you take me into your head and we flash forward to like 2030,
那会是什么样子？
what does it look like?
这就是 Mark Zuckerberg（Meta 创始人兼 CEO）。
This is Mark Zuckerberg.
22 年前，他建立了一个连接数十亿人的社交网络，
Twenty-two years ago, he built a social network that connected billions of people
并永远改变了世界。
and changed the world forever.
但现在他决定构建更宏大的东西来实现这个目标。
But now he's decided to build something even bigger to do it.
他正在 metaverse（元宇宙）、智能眼镜和 AI 上大规模押注。多年来，
He's making massive bets on the metaverse, smart glasses and AI. For years,
怀疑者曾认为这是三场互不相关、不可能成功的豪赌。
skeptics saw these as three separate impossible gambles.
但他们错过了更大的图景，
But they missed the bigger picture
因为现在这些下注正在汇聚，创造出一种全新的
because right now those bets are converging into creating an entirely new kind of
超级智能。
super intelligence.
所以今天，我们要为你展示这一点。
So today, we're going to show you that.
我会问 Mark 一些他从未被问过的问题，
And I'm going to ask Mark questions that he's never been asked before
听听他对未来的愿景，这样你就能提前把握趋势，
and hear his vision for the future so you can get ahead of it
并打造下一件大事。
and build the next big thing.
非常感谢你来节目。是啊，能请到你太激动了。对。
Thanks so much for coming on the show. Yeah, stoked to have you. Yeah.
不，我很兴奋能做这期节目，为了准备这次采访，
No, I'm excited to do this, to prepare for this one,
我看过你做过的每一次采访。
I watched every interview that you've ever done.
好吧？这比我自己看过的还要多。过程很有趣。
Okay? That's more than I've ever done. It was a lot of fun.
真的很棒。
It was great.
有两件大事让我印象深刻。第一，你对构建的热爱。
And like two major things stood out to me. No. 1, your, like, love of building.
我觉得你就是最优秀的构建者之一。
I feel like you're just, like, one of the best builders.
第二，你有能力进行大规模押注。
And then No. 2, your ability to take, like, massive bets.
而我觉得，这一周差不多就是
And I think, like, this week is kind of the week
所有这一切汇聚到一起的一周。
that all of them are coming together.
那我们就从这里开始吧。好。
So let's start there. Yeah.
嗯，是的，我想很多东西我们已经做了很长时间了。
Um, yeah, I guess we've been working on a lot of the stuff for a long time.
我是说，AI 方面的工作，
I mean, the AI work, I mean,
作为一家公司，我们几乎从一开始就在做。
we've kind of been doing as a company, I mean, almost since the beginning.
比如最早版本的 News Feed 从一开始就有点像是
I mean, there's like the first version of News Feed from the beginning is sort of
一种机器学习产品，然后。
this machine learning product and.
所以，是的，有那个版本。
So I mean, yeah, there's, there's that version.
然后是 AI 研究实验室，我们创办它，天哪，差不多是不到 15 年前，
Then the AI research lab, we started, gosh, it's like not quite 15 years ago,
但之后，我们现在进入了一个新阶段，
but then, you know, we're in a new version now
因为大约一年多以前，
because about a little more than a year ago.
我们启动了 Meta（科技公司，原 Facebook）的 Meta Superintelligence Labs（Meta 超级智能实验室）。对，那是一次
We kicked off Meta Superintelligence Labs. Yep. And that was a
对研究进行了一次相当大的重启，引入了业界很多优秀人才。
Kind of wild reboot of the research to bring in a lot of great people from across the industry.
但这很令人兴奋，因为现在，
But it's been exciting cause now, you know,
我们看到模型越来越好。
we're seeing the models get better and better.
我们很快会发布下一代模型。不是在 Connect 大会上，等着吧。
We have, um, uh, the next generation launching soon. Not at Connect, let's go.
然后我们还有 Muse（Meta 的个人 AI 智能体），
Um, but, and then we have, um, you know, Muse, the personal agent that is, you know,
到目前为止，它的反响非常好，甚至可以说是疯狂。
It's, uh, the reception so far has been great, you know, insane.
是的。我是说，在做这类东西时，你并不完全确定。
Yeah. I mean, when you're building this stuff, you don't quite know.
我们自己很喜欢它。对。
I mean, we liked it. Yep.
甚至就在今年早些时候，
Um, you know, even from just earlier in the year, you know,
只是自己在家里拼拼凑凑，把 Claude 搞成一个我自己的版本，
just kind of duct taping together like my own version of Claude at home
去感受，比如，
and getting a sense of like, what?
它到底是怎么运作的？以及，
How does this work? And like, um,
怎样才能把它变成一种可以交给任何人的神奇体验？
what would make this a magical experience that you could give to anyone?
是的，基本上，我一看到那个，我们就基本上，
Yeah, like, basically, as soon as I saw that, you know, we basically,
Nat、Alex 和我坐下来，我们就想，好，
you know, Nat, um, and Alex and I sat down, we were like, okay,
这是一种令人惊叹且神奇的体验。
this is an amazing and magical experience.
如果我们能提供一个版本，
And if we can deliver a version of this
让那些不一定有技术能力、不想自己去
that just works to people who are not necessarily technical enough to want to go
安装自己的 Mac Mini、打开终端进行设置或调试的人也能直接使用，
install their own Mac Mini or get a terminal and set it up or debug stuff
在它出问题时不用自己处理。
when it's not working.
那么我认为，这会成为数十亿人都想使用的东西。
Then I think that this is going to be a thing that billions of people want to use.
所以从那以后，我们基本上一直在朝这个方向努力，你懂的，
So we've basically been working on that over time since then, you know,
让模型专门为此做调优，
getting the models to be tuned specifically for it,
不只是构建 AI agent（AI 智能体）和外围支撑框架，
building not just the agent and the scaffolding,
而且实际上是在构建让每个智能体拥有自己电脑的技术。
but effectively the technology to give every agent its own computer.
我们为此构建了整套 Muse Secure VM（安全虚拟机）。
We built this whole Muse Secure VM.
对，所以我们觉得这个相当特别。
And yeah, so we thought this was pretty special.
公司内部大家也都很喜欢，
And internally, people have really liked it,
但发布一个东西时，你永远不知道人们会怎么反应。
but you never really know when you ship something how people are gonna respond.
而且你知道，偶尔它会是一个——
And, you know, every once in a while it's a,
它会一炮而红，大家从一开始就很喜欢。
it's a home run and people love it out of the gate.
但大多数时候，你会收到一些正面反馈。
But most of the time, you know, you get some feedback that's positive.
你必须先在一些地方不断迭代，它们才会真正对上感觉。
You have to iterate on a few things before they, they kind of really click.
呃，这个真的从一开始就火了。所以它一直——
Um, this one just really clicked right out of the gate. So it's been,
看到这个真的很令人兴奋。
it's been very exciting to see.
对。
Yeah.
而且，事实上我们才，怎么说，
And, and the fact that we're like, what,
才刚两周，就有数百万人在使用，真的，呃，我说不好，
like two weeks in and there's millions of people using it is, um, I don't know,
这非常少见。
this is pretty rare.
我的意思是，每隔几年我们才会遇到一次这样的事，但这绝对——
I mean, every few years we get something like this, but it's, um, this is definitely,
这就是创业过程中最有趣的部分。
you know, the fun part of building a company.
百分之百。对，我觉得你的能力，就是——
Hundred percent. Yeah. I feel like your ability to, like,
一直留在场上、不断尝试，这很令人佩服。
stay in the game and keep trying things is admirable.
而且还有这么多成功产品。真的很棒。
And like also so many hits. Like it's, it's great.
还有一次你做过的采访，
And there was an interview that you did,
大概三年前，和 Joe Rogan 一起，
it was like three years ago with Joe Rogan
采访快结束时你谈到，有一天你会戴上眼镜，
where at the end you were talking about one day you'll like throw on the glasses
然后一个智能体也会跟着出现。
and then like an AI agent will come in as well.
所以我觉得 Muse 现在已经有了实体形象，这个做法很聪明。对。
So I feel like it's so smart that Muse is already embodied. Yeah.
因为这感觉就是未来会发生的事。
Cause that feels like that's what's gonna happen.
对，我觉得这也让它更友好、更可爱。对，同意。
Yeah. I think it also just makes it friendly and cute. Yeah, agree.
这部分的思考是，我觉得很多人把 AI 说成
So part of this is like, I think so many people talk about AI as
好像它是什么超级可怕的东西。对。而且——
if it's this like super scary thing. Yeah. And.
我不知道。
I don't know.
我的意思是，我觉得它应该就是有用、好玩，所以，呃，我——
I mean, I think it, it should just be useful and fun and, um, so I, I,
我觉得那个实体形象，
I thought that that embodiment,
项目早期的一位设计师做出了那个角色，然后，呃。
one of the designers early on in the project put together that character and, um.
不知出于什么原因，他们一直想在它基础上继续改。
And for whatever reason, they kept on trying to iterate on it.
但第一版就是最好的。
But the first one was just the best.
对。
Yeah.
所以，有一阵子有人说，哦，好吧，
So there were like, at some point someone is like, oh, well,
它必须是蓝色，因为这是 Meta，然后，对，不，就是——
it's got to be blue because it's Meta and it's, yeah, no, like,
我觉得这家伙真的……我觉得你第一版就做对了。所以，对，
I think this guy is really like, I think you nailed it on the first try. So, yeah,
不，它就是很好玩。那是——
no, it's it's just fun. That was.
一个很好的点缀。
A good touch.
这会如何改变你训练模型的方式？
How does it change how you like train the model
如果你们想让它特别擅长个人事务，而不是做一个更通用的
if you're trying to make it like really good at personal stuff versus like a general
智能模型？
intelligence model?
嗯，我觉得现在其中一件事，基本上就是要普遍地让
Well, I think one of the things right now is basically there's generally making the
模型成为优秀的智能体，对吧？
models good as agents, okay?
嗯，所以我觉得过去一年，
Um, so I think for the last year,
最重要的事情基本上就是这些编程智能体。
the biggest thing has basically been these coding agents.
这里面其实嵌入了两个概念。
And there are two ideas that are sort of embedded in that.
一个是编程方面的专业能力，另一个是更普遍地成为一个好智能体。
There's the expertise at coding and there's the generally being a good agent.
而我们的策略是。
And our strategy.
编程很重要，因为即使一个人并没有在想
Coding is important because even if a person isn't thinking
自己在写代码，你的 Muse 也会为了帮你做事而在后台写代码，
that they're writing code, your Muse is writing code for you to do all the stuff in
而且它一直在后台做这些。所以，会写代码很重要。
the background all the time. So, so being able to code is important.
但我们基本上采取了这样的策略：我们认为
But we basically took the strategy that we thought
智能体首先应该是一个非常优秀的智能体，所以我们就专注在这一点上。
that the agent should be primarily a great agent and, um, and so we focused on that.
还有很多东西，呃——
There's also a bunch of things that, um,
我认为这些基本上更重要
That, basically, I think, are just more important
当你在构建个人智能体时，比
when you're building a personal agent than
如果你在构建企业软件产品，对吧？
if you're building like an enterprise software, uh, product, right?
比如，如果你在构建 Claude Code，你的模型，
So, for example, if you're building Claude Code, your model,
它不需要具备任何分寸感。
it doesn't need to have any sense of like discretion.
比如什么？对。比如什么该透露、什么不该透露。对，正是。
Like what? Yeah, yeah. Like what to divulge and not divulge. Yeah, exactly.
你怎么看这个问题？嗯，
How do you think about that? Well,
我认为这对 Muse 这样的产品非常重要。
I think that that's a very important thing for something like Muse.
那怎么做到呢？对。我的意思是，你必须把这一点训练到模型里。
So how do you, like, yeah. So I mean, you have to train that into the model.
就像其他能力一样，它需要擅长判断。
I mean, just like any other capability, it needs to be good at knowing.
比如你告诉它很多事情，然后你希望它去实现你的目标。
Like you tell it a lot of things and then you want it to go achieve your goals.
但，比如说，你想让它，比如，
But, you know, let's say you want it to, like,
去帮你预订一家餐厅，然后，
go get you a reservation at a restaurant and, you know,
比如，你想找一家好餐厅，
like, you're trying to find a good restaurant,
但也许你有某种过敏，但你不想透露这种过敏，或者
but maybe you have some allergy but you may not want to like disclose the allergy or
如果你怀孕了之类的情况。但好吧，你希望它……
if you're pregnant or something like that. But okay, you want it like the...
如果你告诉 Muse，它会知道，嗯，
Muse will know if you tell it, um,
而你会希望它能完成任务，但在披露信息时
and you're gonna want to be able to do the job but while disclosing
尽可能少。
as little information as possible.
所以这是一种特定技能，也是
So that's a specific skill and it's something
人们具备的基本社交技能或常识。
that's like kind of basic social skills or common sense that people have.
但如果你只是在构建一个编程智能体，
But if you're just building like a coding agent,
大多数公司并没有把这一点训练进去。
most of these companies haven't trained that in.
这就是我们能做的事情，因为我们做的是全栈，对吧？
So that's like the type of thing that we can do because we're doing the full stack, right?
因为我们在训练模型。
Because we're training the model.
我们不只是拿别人现成的模型
We're not just taking someone else's model off the shelf
然后试图在它周围搭一个脚手架和智能体。
and trying to build a scaffold and an agent around it.
对，我们专门训练整个模型，让它擅长这一点。
Yep, we trained the whole model specifically to be good at that.
显然，它需要在很多方面都擅长，才能做到通用
It obviously needs to be good at a lot of things in order to be generally
智能，但它在这一点上很擅长。
intelligent, but it's good at that.
然后，嗯，你再构建智能体和所有的，
And, um, and then you build the agent and all the,
围绕它的所有细节，从记忆、对，那种框架，
all of the details around it from the memory, the, yep, the kind of harness,
它工作的方式，比如它醒来并检查的“心跳”。
the way that it, like, the heartbeat that it, like, wakes up and checks.
好吧，以下是我了解你的目标。
Okay, here are the goals that I know about you.
现在我能做些什么来帮助推进其中任何一个吗？
Is there anything I can be doing to, to help advance any of those now?
嗯，我们有一整个团队专注于做出好的实时
Um, and we had a whole team that was just focused on making good kind of real time
化身动画。
animations of the avatars.
是的，因为它不只是默认头像。
Yeah, because it's not just like the default Avatar.
你可以制作任何你想要的头像。
You can make whatever Avatar you want.
是的，然后它会自然地进行动画，效果很棒。
Yeah. And then it just like naturally animates and it's awesome.
而且我们正在推出语音模式，你可以
And, you know, we're rolling out this voice mode and you can,
进行实时语音聊天，就像，你的“伙伴”就在那里，
like have a live voice chat and it's just like, and your guy is there,
不管它是什么样，你知道，所以，
like whatever it is, you know, so, um,
所有这些细节，我认为你基本上只有通过做全栈
all these details I think you basically just get from kind of like being full stack
同时做所有模型和产品才能得到。
and doing all the models and the product together.
百分百同意。我觉得另一个重要的事情是虚拟机。
Hundred percent. And I feel like the other big thing is the virtual machine.
嗯，你能解释一下为什么它重要，以及它解锁了什么吗？
Uh huh. Um, can you explain, like, why that matters and what it's unlocked?
好的，我知道有几点。
Yeah. So I know there's a few things.
嗯，基本上，一个智能体要能为你做事，
Um, basically an agent in order to be able to do stuff for you,
就需要一个地方来存储你的信息。
needs a place to store your information.
而且我们认为它不应该只是和其他所有人的信息混在一起，对吧？
And we don't think it should just be like in a pool with everyone else's information, right?
所以你想要，比如，属于你自己的东西。
So you want, like, your own thing.
我觉得可以这样理解：你的智能体会知道很多
I guess one way to think about this is your agent is going to know a lot of
关于你的敏感信息。
sensitive things about you.
比如，当人们开始接触像 Claude 这样的智能体时，
Like, when people started getting into agents like Claude,
他们基本上会在家里弄一台自己的 Mac mini 之类的设备。
they basically got their own like Mac mini thing at home.
所以我们基本上有了这个想法，就是，好吧，很多人，
And so we basically had this idea, which is, okay, like a lot of people,
他们不会想买一台 Mac Mini 或自己设置。
they're not going to want to buy a Mac Mini or set it up.
我们能创造的、能最接近这种体验的最佳方案是什么
What's the best experience that we can create that effectively approximates that
让你只需下载一个应用并注册
so you can just get an app and sign up
然后你会得到一台为你的智能体配置的电脑，用来工作并存储所有
and you get your own computer provisioned for your agent to work with to store all
你的东西，保证安全，并围绕它设计安全模型。这样它
your stuff on, to be secure and to design the security model around that. So that way it.
有点像拥有你自己桌子下面的电脑，你懂的，
Kind of approximates having your own computer under your desk that, you know,
即使像我们这样的公司也无法
even like a company like us isn't going to be able to
如果你使用 Muse Confidential VM，
if you're using the Muse Confidential VM,
这也是我们目前正在做的另一件事。
which is another thing that we're working on now.
我们甚至无法看到你的，呃，你的
Like we won't even be able to see what is on your, um, on, on your,
虚拟机里的内容。
in your virtual machine.
我的意思是，我们围绕这些构建了很多东西。
I mean, there's all these things that we built around that.
还有安全凭据存储，这样当你在处理密码
The secure credential stores, that way when you're doing passwords
之类的东西时，你的智能体不需要能够看到这些。
and stuff like that, your agent doesn't need to be able to see that.
它只需要能够在需要时把它填进去，当它
It just needs to be able to kind of like plug it in when, when it,
当你要求它登录某个东西时，而且只有在你要求时才这么做。
when you ask it to log into something, but only when you ask it to do that.
它的设计方式应该是，这些信息不会随意就能被访问，因为
It should be kind of designed in a way where that information isn't just accessible, because.
我不知道。意外总会发生，对吧？
I don't know. Accidents happen, right?
有人可能试图入侵，或者，呃，或者可能出现问题。
Someone might try to hack into the thing or, um, or there could be an issue.
所以基本上你要把它设置成，智能体根本接触不到
So, so basically you want to set it up so the agent just doesn't have access to
那些信息，而且 Meta 也接触不到。
that and that Meta just doesn't have access to that.
呃，所以给每个智能体一台自己的电脑，并让它尽可能安全
Um, so giving every agent its own computer and making it as secure
是一项非常基础的技术
as possible is just like a very fundamental piece of technology
必须构建出来，才能给
that had to get built in order to give.
Muse 所需的动力，去帮助人们实现目标
Muse both the power that it needs to be able to like go help people with their goals
以及安全和隐私，让它成为世界级、行业领先的
and the security and privacy to be like a kind of world class industry leading
产品。
product in that area.
所以这是说，你使用 Muse 时，它会有一个虚拟机
So does that mean like you use Muse and it has a virtual machine
它连接到这个虚拟机，但所有数据都以同样的方式加密
that it's connected to, but all the data is encrypted in the same way
就像在 WhatsApp 上加密一样。
that it's encrypted on WhatsApp.
那人们该怎么理解数据实际是什么样子
Like how can people think about what the data actually looks like
当它存放在虚拟机里的时候？
when it's living in the virtual machine?
是的，我们基本上做了两个版本：Muse Secure VM，好吧，
Yeah, so we basically built two versions: Muse Secure VM, okay,
它具备所有这些不同的隐私功能，包括，你知道，我们
has all these different privacy features including, you know, we,
我们构建了整套 Sentinel 智能体架构。
we built this whole Sentinel agent architecture.
所以你有普通的 Muse 智能体帮你做事，
So you have your normal Muse agent that's doing stuff for you,
然后还有一个我们称为 Sentinel 的安全智能体
and then you basically have the security agent that we call Sentinel
专门监控进出你 Muse 的数据。
that is just monitoring the data going in and out to your Muse.
所以如果，呃，有什么东西进来，有人试图，比如，比如
So if, um, something comes in and someone's trying to, like, like,
破坏安全性，它就会直接切断，确保这种事不会发生。
compromise the security, it'll just cut it off and make it so it doesn't happen.
如果它认为你的 Muse 要执行某个操作。——对。
If it thinks that your Muse is going to take an action. Yep.
一个需要你参与确认的操作，
That you should be in the loop on,
它基本上会覆盖你的 Muse，并触发
it will basically override your Muse and trigger
回到你本人来请求权限。
that back to the person to say for permissions.
就像问：你想让你的 Muse 能这样做吗？
It's like, do you want your Muse to be able to do this?
实际上这整个是一组系统群，然后
It's actually this whole kind of constellation of systems and
再加上 Secure Credential 存储，呃，
that plus the Secure Credential storage plus, um,
通过，呃，纵深方向的多层安全。
just like several layers of security through, through, um, through depth there.
我们，呃，构成了 Muse Secure VM。
We, um, make up the, the Muse Secure VM.
我们还在做另一件事，Nat
We're also working on this other thing that Nat
和我专门请来了 Moxie Marlinspike，
and I specifically recruited Moxie Marlinspike,
就是和我们一起做 WhatsApp 加密的那个人，
the guy who we worked with to do the WhatsApp encryption,
来设计 Muse Confidential VM。
to design the Muse Confidential VM.
它背后的想法是，在所有这些之上，
And the idea behind that is that, on top of everything else,
它是一个你能拿到加密密钥的虚拟机。
it is a virtual machine where you get an encryption key.
这样连 Meta 也无法访问其中的内容。
So that way Meta can't even access the contents of that.
呃，它实现起来要难得多，因为显然
Um, it's much harder to implement because obviously
如果 Meta 无法访问里面的内容，调试就会困难很多。
if Meta can't access what's within it, then it's a lot harder to debug.
也就更难把系统跑通。
So, and get the system working.
所以，把它发布出来花了我们一点时间，但是，呃，
So, like, it's taking us a little bit of time to get that shipped, but, um,
但它很快会推出，基本上会成为安全标准
but that's coming soon and it's basically going to be the standard of security
就像人们在 WhatsApp 上习惯的那种，以及在某些
that people are used to for WhatsApp and in some.
呃，我们最安全的产品上。
Um, you know, our most secure products like that.
这种做法的优势是不是只是心理上的，人们会觉得它更……
And is the advantage of that just like psychologically people will think it's more
安全，还是确实有实际好处？
secure or are there actually benefits?
嗯，不。我是说，我觉得，嗯，我觉得安全确实是件大事。
Well, no. I mean, I think that that, well, I think that that security is a big deal.
我是说，如果我们再次试图去近似拥有，
I mean, it's, if, if we're, we're trying to, again, approximate having,
你有一个智能体，运行在桌下的本地机器上。
you have an agent with a local machine under your desk.
对。那当你桌下有台本地机器时，你会得到什么？
Yeah. So what do you get when you have the local machine under your desk?
这意味着没有任何公司能访问它。所以，好，
That means that no company has access to it. So, okay,
假设 Meta 想为你提供这项服务。
let's say Meta wants to offer you the service.
我们该怎样让你拥有同样级别的隐私和安全保障，
How do we make it so you have that same level of privacy and security guarantee
也就是没有公司——这里说的是 Meta，或者，你知道，
that no company, in this case Meta or, you know,
任何试图入侵我们的人，或者如果你在某个国家，
anyone who tries to hack into us or if you're in some country
你不信任那里的政府，
where you don't trust the government,
如果政府可能试图让我们做些什么。
if the government might try to get us to do something.
就像我们做不到，我们无法进入它，因为我们没有访问权限。
It's like we can't, we can't get into it because we don't have access to it.
这一点真的很重要。这是很多人觉得 WhatsApp 让人放心的很大原因。
And that that really matters. That's a lot of why people feel comfortable with WhatsApp.
完全可以理解。
Totally.
嗯，所以我觉得这真的、这真的很重要，对于
Um, so that I think is a real, that's a real thing for,
隐私、安全和信任来说都很重要，而且如果你要有一个智能体，
for privacy and security and trust and if you're gonna have an agent
它非常了解你，我猜我们几乎所有人都会有
that knows a lot about you, which I would guess pretty much we all are going to have
那种。我是说，我觉得你……
that. I mean, I think you.
快进到五年后，几乎每个人都会有一个智能体，
Fast forward five years, like everyone is gonna have an agent
它能非常深入地理解你的目标和你周围的一切，而且，嗯，
that like really intimately understands your goals and everything around you and, um,
还能帮你把事情做成。
and can help you get stuff done.
而要做到这一点，我认为，
And in order to do that, I think that,
在隐私和安全上达到那个水平、做到行业领先，非常重要。
that level and being industry leading in privacy and security is very important.
我们希望从一开始就做到这一点。这很酷。嗯。
We want to do that from the beginning. That's cool. Yeah.
还有一件关于你的事很有意思，你在大学学过心理学。对。
Something also very interesting about you is that you studied psychology in college. Yeah.
嗯，我在那里待的时间很短。对，两年。
Um, when I was there for a very short period of time. Yeah, two years.
对。但我觉得这影响了你后来构建的很多东西。
Yeah. But I feel like it's kind of informed a lot of what you've built.
嗯，所以我很好奇，比如我们看基准测试时，
Um, and so I'm curious, like when we look at benchmarks,
很多时候我们会觉得，嗯，这个模型超级聪明。
a lot of times we'll be like, um, the model is super smart.
嗯，但这也有点像我们选择朋友时，
Um, but it also feels like when we pick our friends,
我们当然会因为朋友聪明而选择他们，
we definitely pick our friends because they're smart,
但我们一定也会因为喜欢他们的能量、喜欢和他们相处而选择他们。
but we also definitely pick them because we like their energy or being around them.
嗯，你怎么看塑造模型以及它的人格？
Um, how do you think about shaping the model and like the personality?
对，我是说，我觉得理想情况下它会有足够的可适应性，能够
Yeah, I mean, I think ideally it will be adaptable enough to be able to.
贴合不同人的能量，对吧？
Fit different people's energy, right?
我觉得这其实是
I think this is actually something
我认为行业里很多人搞错的一点。
that I think a lot of people get wrong in the industry.
你知道，很多其他实验室，我觉得，一直专注于
You know, a lot of the other labs, I think, have focused on like,
如何把人格做对。
how do we get the personality right?
对。
Yeah.
而我从来不觉得它只有一种样子。
And I just never thought that it's one thing
这也是我如此坚信开源的部分原因，
and this is part of the reason why I believe so strongly in open source
以及人们能够自定义各种东西，
and people being able to customize stuff
也是为什么我们把 Muse 设计成非常个人化的东西。
and also why we designed Muse to be this thing that is very personal.
你可以个性化它，也可以自定义它。
You can personalize it and customize it.
你不仅可以设置虚拟形象和声音的方式，
You can kind of set up not just the avatar and the voice the way
你想要的，而且就在你第一次注册时，
that you want, but like right when you sign up for the first time,
它最先让你做的一件事就是，
one of the first things that it asks you to do is like.
你希望我的基本人格是什么？而且你可以随时去编辑。
What do you want my basic personality to be? And you can go and edit it at any time.
所以我们努力把模型设计得非常易于引导。
So we try to design the models to be very steerable.
这样你就可以定义自己希望怎么与它互动。
That way you can kind of define how you want to interact with it.
我认为这一点非常重要。
And I think that that's a really important thing.
我是说，你刚才在问，我们如何让它变得足够好。
I mean, you were asking about, like, how do we make it so that this is good.
作为个人智能体，我认为拥有
As a personal agent, I think that like having
人格上的那种可适应性，是其中很重要的一部分。
that adaptability around the personality is, is a big part of it.
你的那个又是什么样？如果要你描述它的特征呢？
What's yours like? Like if you were to describe its traits?
我觉得它是，我想我只是让它相当直接、偏工作风格，
I think it's, I think I just told it to be like pretty direct and like work-like,
嗯，所以，我是说，我不确定。
um, so, I mean, I don't know.
我觉得，我觉得这挺好玩。
I think, I think it's kind of fun.
我之前有个版本挺毒舌、挺幽默的，但，嗯，我不确定。
An earlier version I had was pretty sarcastic and humorous, but, um, I don't know.
这个版本，我觉得就是更直接一点。
This incarnation of it, I think it's just a little more straightforward.
对，呃，是的，我那位就是普通的默认 Muse 角色，
Yeah, it's, um, yeah, my, my guy is like the normal default Muse, um, character,
但我给他穿了件托加袍。
but I give him a toga.
哦。而且他就是有一种，怎么说，那种，呃。
Ooh. And he has, and he just has this like, kind of like, um.
嗓音低沉到有点好笑。
Extremely deep, to the point of being humorous, voice.
跟他互动就是很好玩。
And it's just like a fun thing to engage with.
对，对。我觉得要搞笑，你得非常聪明。
Yeah, yeah. I feel like to be funny you have to be really smart.
我觉得很多人不懂，喜剧演员其实是最聪明的一批人。
Like, I think a lot of people don't get, like, comedians are some of the smartest.
对，对。
Yeah, yeah.
你得反应快。对，你得非常机智。嗯，
You gotta be fast. Yeah. You gotta be like quick-witted. Um,
这绝对是你有的特质之一。
one of the traits you definitely have.
嗯，我很好奇，你确实有。
Um, I'm curious, like, I mean, you totally do.
我看了你所有的采访，觉得你一直都很棒。
I feel like watching all the interviews, you're always great.
呃，你和 Theo Von，你们都很友善，真的很友善。
Uh, you and Theo Von, you're very nice. You're very nice.
我是认真的。不过好，说到这个，在 Theo Von 的采访里，
I mean it, um, but okay, on that note, in the Theo Von interview,
你们聊了很多关于技术的下一个前沿，
you guys talk a lot about like this next frontier of like technology
以及这一切最终在构建什么。
and what it's all building towards.
嗯，我经常想到 AI 曾经有过那种，
Um, and I think about a lot like with AI, there were these,
寒冬期，人们会说这永远不会发生。
like winter seasons where people be like, this is never gonna happen.
好像不会有什么突破。
Like, no breakthroughs are coming.
嗯，感觉 metaverse 也经历了好几次这样的阶段，
Um, it feels like the metaverse has had several of those
人们觉得那是一个下注，但后来没有兑现。
where people kind of think it's a bet that then doesn't come to fruition.
我昨天试了新的全息功能。我知道那个挺酷的。
I tried out yesterday the new hologram feature. I know it's pretty cool.
对。
Yeah.
因为你们上次做采访的时候，
Because in the last interview you guys did,
我记得光是把你的脸弄进去，设置就要花 11 个小时。
I feel like it was like an 11-hour setup to get your face in there.
对，对。现在只要三分钟。对，嗯，就是这样。
Yeah, yeah. And now it's three minutes. Yeah. Um, that's how it goes.
那接下来会有什么？还有，
What's coming with that? And like,
是什么突破把我们带到了这一刻？
what were the breakthroughs that led us to this moment?
对。
Yeah.
所以，总的来说，元宇宙的发展，嗯，
So, I mean, overall, the development of the metaverse, um,
有意思的是，我们创立 Reality Labs 的时候，就一直觉得，
it's interesting because when we started Reality Labs, we always thought, you know,
你会先看到外观普通的眼镜，
you're gonna get like normal looking pairs of glasses
随着时间推移，它们能同时做到两件事。
and over time they're going to be able to do both.
既提供沉浸式的临场感，又是一个强大的 AI 设备，
Deliver this immersive sense of presence as well as being a great AI device
因为眼镜是唯一一种形态，
because glasses are the only form factor
能让设备看到你看到的、听到你听到的，
where you can let the device see what you see and hear what you hear
还能整天在你耳边说话，最终显示图像。对。
and talk to you in your ear throughout the day and eventually display images. Yep.
但你知道，大概 10 到 15
But, you know, 10 or 15.
年前，我还以为我们会先得到全息技术，然后才会出现非常先进的 AI。
Years ago, I just assumed we'd get holograms before we got very advanced AI.
但我觉得，有趣的是科技树发展的方式，
But I think, like, it's this funny thing about the way the tech tree has worked
我们实际上是先迎来 AI 和个人超级智能，
that we actually are just getting AI and, like, personal superintelligence
然后才真正拥有让全息技术普及的技术，
before we actually get the technology to make holograms ubiquitous
并且便宜到人人都能用。所以我之前不会预测到。
and affordable enough for everyone to use. So I wouldn't have predicted.
不过我很高兴我们两条路线都在做，而且，
That, but I'm glad we're working on both and the fact
我们在眼镜上做的这些工作，确实让我们，
that we are doing all this work on glasses has definitely just made it so
现在所有这些智能体都准备好了，我们处于非常有利的位置。
that we are sort of very well positioned now that all these AI agents are ready.
所以我们在 Connect 大会上基本上要宣布的很多内容，就是把 Muse
So a lot of what we're basically announcing at Connect is bringing Muse
和很多 AI 功能带到眼镜上，嗯，
and a lot of AI functionality to the glasses um,
我认为人们会非常喜欢。
in a way that I think people are really gonna love.
所以这是件大事。
So that's, that's a big deal.
不过，关于临场感的一些工作，
Um, but yeah, some of the stuff around presence,
我们仍然在后台慢慢推进，
we're still working on it a little bit slower burn in the background
因为我们确实把大部分重点转移到了
because we've definitely shifted most of our focus to,
为眼镜构建所有 Muse 和 AI 功能上。
to building all the Muse and AI features for the glasses.
但我们做了有一阵子的一个项目是，嗯，
But one of the projects that we've had for a while has been, um,
就是那种实时的、照片级真实感的虚拟形象。
has been the real-time, kind of like, photorealistic avatars.
没错。
Totally.
是啊，就像你说的，以前，呃，
And, yeah, I mean, like you said, it used to be, uh,
大概三四年前，你需要，
maybe like three or four years ago, you needed,
差不多一整个房间才能从所有角度扫描一个人。
like a whole room in order to scan someone from all the angles.
对。
Yeah.
然后就算你能体验到，但你需要，呃，
And then if you could like experience it, but you needed like, uh,
像是自己的 GPU，得在那种企业级配置里才能
like your own GPU like in the kind of like enterprise-grade setup to be able
做到，对。
to do it, so yeah.
所以我们把它做成了我参加 Lex 播客时的一个演示。
So we set that up as a demo for the Lex podcast that I did.
对。那大概是几年前吧？对。
Yeah. Was that maybe like a couple of years ago? Yeah.
而且，嗯，对，我觉得这些事情发展的方式就是，
And, um, and yeah, I mean, I think the way that these things work is, like,
你先努力把它做好，对吧？
first you try to just make it good, yeah?
然后再努力让它更高效。
And then you try to make it more efficient.
所以现在我们基本上已经让它能在这副 VR 眼镜里运行了。
So now we basically have it working in this pair of VR glasses.
对，也就是说，这是第一副，
Yeah, which is, I mean, this is the first pair of like,
第一个真正惊艳的 VR 体验，能装进一副眼镜里，
the first like amazing VR experience that is in a pair of glasses,
而不是一个大头显，因为我觉得很多人不想要一整个头显。
not a big headset because I think a lot of people don't want to have a whole headset.
对。而且，嗯，对，你现在基本上只需设置你的 Avatar（虚拟化身），用，呃，
Yeah. And, um, and yeah, you basically just set up your Avatar with, like,
现在用几张照片就行。
a few photos at this point.
就是，它的进步真的很惊人。对。
It's like, but it's pretty amazing how far it's come. Yeah.
而且它也是基于声音的。真的，那个演示太有意思了。
And it's also based on the voice. Like, it was so interesting in the demo.
嗯，基本上它让我笑、互动，
Um, basically it had me, like, laugh and interact
然后理解我的脸会怎么动。
and then understand how my face would move.
对，根据音轨。
Yeah, with the audio track.
嗯，在那个播客里很有趣，
Um, it was interesting in that podcast,
你谈到那些可能不那么有表情的人，实际上会想要变得
you talked about how people that maybe are less expressive will actually want to be
在虚拟世界里更丰富地表达自己，我觉得。
more expressive in like the virtual world, I think.
所以你怎么看人们划清他们的虚拟自我
So how do you think about people like delineating between like their virtual self
和现实生活中的自我之间的界限？
and then like their in real life self?
嗯，我觉得我们在理解相关社会学
Um, I think we're still pretty early in understanding the sociology
和心理学方面还很早期。
and psychology around that.
我的意思是，我觉得人们会，
I mean, I think people are going to,
我觉得人们如何看待自己，以及他们想呈现出来的样子，往往
I think that often how people perceive themselves and what they want to project is
和他们真实的样子有些不同，对吧？
somewhat different from what they actually are, right?
我的意思是，从社交网络早期开始，
I mean, people, I mean, from the beginning of social networks,
人们就会精心挑选头像照片。
people have curated profile photos.
嗯，对，我们在虚拟化身、在 Muse 上看到了这种趋势的一种版本。
Um, yeah, we're seeing a version of this with the avatars, with Muse.
对。而且那不再是精心打理你自己，
Yeah. And that's less curating yourself,
而更像是精心设计你想要对话的那个“人”。
but it's like curating like your guy that you want to talk to.
所以，嗯，对。
So, um, yeah.
不，我觉得这会非常有趣。
No, I think it's gonna be very interesting
但我觉得，每当你给人们表达自己是谁的能力时——
but I think like whenever you're giving people the ability to express who they are.
对。
Yeah.
我不认为你希望它只是一种捕捉他们真实样子的东西，但你也希望它，
I don't think you want it to be something that can capture them, but you also want them,
它既是一种表达形式，也像是一种传达。
it is also a form of expression as much as it's a form of, like, conveying.
它不应该只是一面纯粹的镜像。它应该是，
It's not meant to just be a pure mirror image. It's meant to be a,
一种表达方式。
a form of expression.
所以，嗯，对，我觉得我们希望能打造一种两者兼备的东西。
So, um, so yeah, I think we want to be able to build something that can do both.
而这始终是一个迭代循环。
And this is always this iterative loop
你想先看看人们怎么使用这些东西，然后再去改进，
where you want to see how people use the stuff and then you go work on it
把它做得更好。
and make it better.
但是，但我认为我们现在才基本站在这件事的起跑线上。
But, but I think we're, we're basically at the starting line of this now
经过多年努力后，我们现在才真正要把它做成产品。
after many years of work, we're now actually going to get it into products.
而且我们第一次将拥有这些相当高质量的
And for the first time, we're going to have these like pretty high quality
照片级真实的虚拟化身，你可以在手机上做到，
photorealistic avatars that you can, you'll be able to do it on your phone,
也可以在 VR 里做到。
you'll be able to do it in VR.
嗯，所以，对，我很有兴趣看看这会怎么发展。
Um, so yeah, I'm, I'm quite interested to see how that goes.
好，所以如果你带我进入你的大脑，我们快进到 2030 年，呃，
Okay, so like if you take me into your head and we flash forward to like 2030, um,
如果一切顺利，那会是什么样子？
what does it look like if that goes right?
比如说，在全息影像那一侧，有了这项技术，普通的一天会是什么样？
Like what's the average day with that technology on the hologram side,
比如全息影像加 Muse，它们会怎样和眼镜融合在一起。
like hologram plus Muse, like how they're kind of like converging with the glasses.
对，我一直认为 metaverse 愿景的核心始终是。
Yeah. So I mean, the way that I think about the metaverse vision was always about.
有效地把物理世界和数字世界融合在一起。所以……
Effectively bringing together the physical and digital worlds. So the.
基本想法是，我们身边已经有了一个很棒的物理世界，
The basic idea is like we have this great physical world around us,
但同时我们也有一个很棒的数字世界，
but we also have a great digital world where, you know,
它建立在互联网上，至今已经有二三十年了。
it's just been built on the internet for, you know, 20, 30 years at this point.
那里有海量内容，非常惊人。
And there's like all this content. It's pretty amazing.
而我们访问它的主要方式，要么是坐在桌前，要么是通过
And then the main ways that we access it are either by sitting at a desk or through
我们口袋里那块小屏幕。
this, like, small screen in our pocket.
这从根本上来说非常受限，对吧？就像你……
And that seems, like, fundamentally very limiting, right? It's like what you.
我认为理想的形态应该是物理世界
I think the ideal version of this would be a seamless blending of the physical
和数字世界无缝融合。
and digital world.
我觉得可以这样想：
And I think the way to think about this is, okay,
现在，我们两个人是物理上在这里。
so right now the two of us are here physically.
你可以想象未来的一种版本，
You can imagine a version of this in the future where, you know,
其中一个人是全息影像，但你仍然有同样的临场感，
one of us is a hologram, but you kind of have the same sense of presence,
就像你真的和某个人在同一个地方。
like feeling like you're there with someone physically.
这跟 Zoom 通话之类完全不同。对吧。
It's very different from like a Zoom call or something like that. Right.
不过虚拟现实的核心就在于
So, um, but the, the whole thing about virtual reality is
它能带来这种临场感，
that it delivers this sense of presence
让你真正感觉自己和另一个人在一起，或者身处另一个地方。
where you actually feel like you are there with another person or in another place.
所以你可以用全息影像做到这一点，也可以用不同方式混合。
So you could do that with a hologram and you can have that mixed in different ways.
比如，你可以想象，
So I mean, you could have like,
我可以和朋友们打扑克，
I could have a poker night with my friends
一半人物理到场。
where like half of us are there physically.
对。
Yep.
然后几个人通过全息影像加入，也能打牌，
And, you know, a few people join through a hologram and can play cards
也许扑克牌也是全息影像的一部分，
and maybe the cards are part of the hologram
这样我们也能给不在场的人发牌。
so we can kind of deal in the people who are not there physically.
对。
Yep.
但我认为 AI 也可以拥有具体形象并出现在现场，这……
Um, but then I think AI can also just be embodied and be there too, which, I mean,
也许扑克之夜不是最好的例子，但在工作中，
maybe poker night isn't the best example, but like in work,
我认为这很有意义。
I think that makes sense.
对，对。我们已经在和各种智能体一起工作。
Yeah, yeah. And we already are like working with all these agents.
比如我经常用不同的编程智能体来构建东西。
Like, I use different coding agents to build stuff all the time.
你可以想象这样的具象化场景：
So you think about, like, all right, you have the embodiment where, like,
也许你在一个群聊频道里，有几个人
maybe you're in a group chat channel where there's like a few people
还有几个智能体，你正在给这些智能体下达指令。
and like a couple of agents and you're giving the agents directions for what to do.
但也有对应的物理空间版本，
But there's also like the physical version of that where, all right,
有时人们聚在一起开会，
sometimes the people get together in a meeting and like, I don't know,
也许智能体也应该参加那个会议。
maybe the agents should be in that meeting too.
那它们会怎么出现？
So how would they show up?
就像这样，它们……嗯，
It's like, alright, they, well,
沙发上有几个空位，没错，
there's a couple of extra spots on the couch and yeah,
它们可以以全息影像的形式出现，就在那里，
they can just come and be a hologram and be there and, um,
或者无论具象化形式是什么，你可以得到 Muse 里那个可爱的小角色，或者
or whatever the embodiment is, you get the cute little character from Muse or
随便什么，龙或者你创造的任何疯狂形象。嗯，我……
whatever, dragon or whatever, like crazy thing you create. Um, I.
我觉得那将会……我觉得那会……它会……我，
Think that that's gonna be, I think that's gonna, it'll, I,
我猜未来这会让人感到非常自然。
my guess is that that will end up feeling quite natural in the future.
对，所以我觉得这些东西会融合在一起。
Yeah. So I think that these things will come together.
显然，只用文本也能让 AI 走得很远，
You can obviously get very far with the AI with just text,
但我认为，我们开始在一些实时系统中看到，
but I think what we're starting to see with some of the real-time systems
能够看到那个……
around being able to, you know, see the.
具象化的角色和实时互动，人们很喜欢。
The character embodied and like the real-time interactions like people like that.
它很可爱，很有趣。
It's cute, it's fun.
你会觉得你真的在跟它说话。这很酷。
Like you feel like you're there talking to the thing. It's like, it's cool.
所以我认为我们最终也想要在眼镜体验中拥有这些。
So I think we're gonna eventually want that in the glasses experience too.
对，这很有意思，因为你之前在一次采访里说过
Yeah, it's interesting cause you said in a previous interview
你觉得科技行业经常忘记“有趣”这件事。
that you feel like the tech industry often forgets fun.
对，对。
Yeah, yeah.
我觉得，让智能体出现在那里……
And I think like, having the agent be there, um,
它也会让你感觉更真实，就像你在把工作外包出去。
It also just makes it feel more real, like you're outsourcing work.
当你看到 Muse 在打字之类的，你会觉得真的有事在发生。
When you see Muse typing and stuff, it feels like something is actually happening.
对，对。
Yeah, yeah.
嗯，我觉得很多……我觉得 ChatGPT 在这一点上做得很好，
Um, and I think a lot of, like, I think ChatGPT did a great job with that,
它的浏览器能看到正在发生什么。
with the browser being able to see, like, what's going on.
嗯，你觉得会不会有一天你戴上眼镜
Um, do you think there's a world in which you wear the glasses
就能控制你的电脑？
and then you control your computer?
就像你有 Muse，它在你的电脑上帮你做事。
It's like you have Muse and it's doing stuff on your computer.
哦，是的，绝对。我的意思是，VR 已经能做到这个了。我是说，
Oh, yeah, definitely. I mean, the VR, uh, already does that. I mean,
你基本上可以坐在任何你想坐的地方。
you can basically, like, sit down anywhere you want.
对，咖啡店，随便哪里。
Yeah, coffee shop, whatever.
你打开工作站，有六块显示器，你在写代码，
You pull up your workstation, you have, like, six monitors, you're coding,
你什么都有。
you have, like, all that stuff.
然后，嗯，我们基本上在眼镜这边，
And then, um, we—we basically, on the glasses side,
现在最受欢迎的眼镜还没有内置显示屏，
the most popular glasses don't have displays in them yet,
这既让它更便宜，也让更多人能用上。
which both allows us to make it more affordable, so more people can use it.
但我们也还在努力把它做成最紧凑的形态。
But also we're still working on getting that into, like, the most compact form factor.
但我们确实推出了 Meta Ray-Ban 显示版。
But we did launch the Meta Ray-Ban displays.
它们非常受欢迎。对，是个小显示屏。
They've been quite popular. Yeah, it's a small display.
我们还推出了，嗯，那个，就像，
We also launched the, um, the, like, the,
完整宽视场全息 AR 的原型版本，而且
the prototype version of the full wide-field-of-view holographic AR, and
我觉得那款会非常令人兴奋。
that one I think is going to be very exciting.
所以我觉得你基本上会看到整个产品线，从这些——
So I think you're basically just gonna get this whole lineup from, I mean, these guys
这些是纯音频眼镜。
are the audio-only glasses.
所以，这些甚至连摄像头都没有。
So, I mean, these, like, they don't even have a camera.
它们看起来就像完全普通的眼镜，
They just look like completely normal glasses,
但里面装着你的 Muse，你可以用所有音频工具。
but you have your Muse in them and you can get, you know, all the audio tools.
你可以听音乐、接电话。
You can listen to music, you can take phone calls.
我在想，用那些眼镜的话，
I guess I'm thinking with those, like,
你能不能一边和 Muse 说话，一边让家里的台式机做事？
could you, like, be talking to Muse and have your desktop at home doing stuff?
哦，对，完全可以。这个其实，
Oh, yeah, totally. Well, that's—that's actually,
我们其实刚刚在 Connect 上发布了。
we just actually shipped that at Connect.
对，我是说，基本上现在所有眼镜都连接到 Meta AI。
Yeah, I mean, we're—we're basically today, all the glasses connect to Meta AI.
所以这类似于单轮体验：你给它一个提示词，它回复，然后就结束。
So it's sort of this one-turn experience. You give it a prompt, it replies, that's the end.
但现在有了 Muse，我们基本上会把它们全部升级到 Muse。
But with Muse now, we're basically gonna upgrade them all to Muse.
所以首先，你不用再说“Hey Meta”了。
So first of all, you don't say, "Hey, Meta," anymore.
你可以随便给它起名字，这也是乐趣的一部分。
You just get to name it whatever you want, which, again, is like part of the fun.
所以我会说，“Hey, Agrippa”，对。
So I was like, "Hey, Agrippa," yeah.
然后，嗯，然后基本上它，呃，对，不，
And then, um, and then basically it, uh, yeah, no,
然后你就直接跟它说话，它会，呃，
and then you just talk to it and it, it's, uh,
它会连接到你的 Muse，你的 Muse 会在你的安全 VM 里工作，
it connects to your Muse, and your Muse goes and does work in your secure VM, and
然后帮你把事情做完。
and gets stuff done for you.
对，这太棒了。
Yeah, that's epic.
对，我超喜欢。对，会很好玩。那么，好，
Yeah, no, I love that. Yeah, it's gonna be very fun. So, okay,
我们现在坐在这里，Muse 进展很好，眼镜也表现不错。
we're sitting here now and Muse has gone really well and the glasses have done well.
但大约一年前，我感觉很多人都在说，
But about a year ago, I feel like a lot of people were like,
Super Intelligence Lab 到底怎么了？
what is going on with Super Intelligence Lab?
嗯，在那一刻，你内心是什么感觉？
Um, in that moment, what does that feel like to you?
在你脑海里，当事情进展不顺利时是什么感觉，
Like in your head, what does it feel like when things aren't going well
但你还能看到那幅长期愿景？
but you see, like, the long-term vision?
嗯，好吧，真正偏离轨道的事情是，呃。
Um, well, okay, so the thing that really was off track was, um,
Llama 项目和 Llama 4，你知道，Llama，Llama 1 是，
The Llama program and Llama 4, you know—Llama, Llama 1 was,
作为一个模型很有意思，
was quite interesting as a model
它算是开创了整个开源 AI，对，
and it sort of pioneered the whole open-source AI, yep,
这个运动，我认为非常强大，而且也是
movement, which I think has been very powerful and is something
我们非常自豪的事情。
that we're very proud of.
然后 Llama 2 规模化了。Llama 3 是一个非常不错的模型。
And Llama 2 scaled. Llama 3 was a very good model.
它当时几乎已经在前沿了。
It was almost at the frontier at the time.
然后到了 Llama 4，我们基本偏离了原本需要的轨道。
And then with Llama 4, we basically fell off the trajectory that we needed to be on.
而我的反思是，
And I was, my reflection on this,
每当事情没有按照我认为应该的方向发展
whenever something doesn't go the way that I think it should,
我总会花很多时间思考：为什么会这样？
I always spend a bunch of time thinking about like why did that happen?
我们需要改变什么来让它更好？而在这件事上，我的……
What do we need to change to make it better? And in this case, my.
我的反思是，我在团队的整体形态上搞错了
My reflection was that the whole kind of shape of the team I had gotten wrong.
所以我借鉴了我们之前做机器学习工作的方式，来打造
So I modeled it off of the way that we'd done our machine learning work for making
比如 Instagram 信息流或广告系统之类的东西
like Instagram feed or or ad system or something like this.
这些团队有数百甚至数千人，可以并行处理
These teams that have like many hundreds or thousands of people who can work on a
大量工作
lot of stuff in parallel.
而我认为，构建这些语言模型时
Whereas I think for building these language models,
你真正需要的只是一个非常紧密的团队，把它看作
what you really want is just a very tight knit team that views it
一个小组科学项目
as like a group science project.
所以不需要很多人，这意味着团队里每个位置都极其宝贵
So not many people, which means that every seat on that team is extremely valuable.
所以我们最终从整个 Meta 内部引入了一批最优秀的人加入团队
So we ended up bringing a bunch of the best people from across Meta into the team,
同时也从整个行业引入了很多优秀人才进来
but also bringing a lot of other awesome people from around the industry in
并组建了一个全新的团队，我们称之为 Meta Superintelligence Labs
and building a completely new team which we called Meta Super Intelligence Lab.
所以在我看来，到那个时候
So from my perspective, by the time that.
我们创立 MSL 时，嗯，就知道要花一些时间重新调整，并
We were starting MSL, um, we knew it was gonna take some time to kind of reboot and
也重建基础设施，来构建下一套模型，对
and like rebuild the infrastructure to build the next set of models yeah.
嗯，但我知道我们能组建出一支很棒的团队，也知道
Um, but I knew that we'd pull together a great team and I knew that
如果能让团队融合并良好运转，那就很好
if we could kind of like gel the team and have that work well, then it would be good.
对
Yeah.
对我来说，最可怕的时刻其实是 Llama 4 发布之后
To me, actually, the scariest moment was after the Llama 4 launch
当时感觉就是：哦，我以为我们在这条轨道上，结果没有
when it was just like, oh, I thought we were on this trajectory and we're not.
对，这算是一个相当大的负面意外
Yeah. And it was sort of like a, a pretty big negative surprise.
我觉得，你知道，当你作为创业者时
And I think like, yeah, you know, when you're an entrepreneur,
你在构建一些东西，我认为你
you're building something, I think you,
你会在那些时刻受到考验
you kind of get tested in those moments
因为不可避免的是，不是所有事情都会顺利，而那些
because inevitably like not everything is gonna go well and the things
真正决定发展轨迹的是，好吧
that kind of define the trajectory are like, okay.
如果某件事没有按你希望的方式发展，你如何，嗯，如何
If something doesn't go the way that you want, how do you, um, how do,
你如何基本弄清楚该如何继续前进？
how do you basically kind of figure out how to move forward?
对，我猜也有另一面
Yeah, I guess there's the flip side of that too,
当某件事比你预期的好得多时
when something goes way better than you expect.
是的，比如 Muse 的首次发布，你如何确保自己抓住这个机会？
Yeah. Like the initial Muse launch, how do you just make sure you capitalize on that?
完全是这样
Totally.
现在整个公司上下都在大规模投入这件事
And now we have this like, like whole big effort across the company
起初还只是……
where it's like first it was just the,
负责构建产品的小团队在做，但现在所有人都觉得，好吧
the team that was working on it to kind of build a product but now everyone is like, okay.
这真的已经准备好全面推广了
This, this is actually ready for prime time.
所以我们如何把它做大，并帮助人们
So how do we basically grow this and, and like and help people,
帮助数亿人体验这个，由全公司一起推动
help hundreds of millions of people experience this from across the company.
所以看到每个人都参与进来，并且
So it's pretty cool to see everyone kind of chip in and,
并全力确保我们能扩展 Muse，涵盖从……
and work on totally making sure that we can scale Muse out everything from just
真正优化所有基础设施，让它运转得非常好
really optimizing all the infrastructure to make it work really well.
尽可能从我们现有的 GPU 中挤出更多能力
Squeeze as much capacity as we can out of the GPUs that we have.
对
Yeah.
嗯，但所有产品团队也在以不同的方式构建 Muse
Um, but then all the product teams too kind of building Muse in in different ways
比如眼镜，嗯，对，看到这些非常有趣
like the glasses and, um, yeah, no, it's, it's a, it's very fun to see.
是的，我觉得作为创始人，那就是你梦寐以求的时刻
Yeah, I feel like as a founder, that's like the moment that you live for,
一切汇聚到一起
where it's like, it all comes together.
嗯，你如何向公司阐述你的愿景？
Um, how do you articulate your vision to the company?
当你在做这么多不同的事情时
Like when you're working on so many different things, like,
我感觉你经常写作
I feel like you write a lot.
你的流程是怎样的？
What's, like, your process?
是的，写作对我很有帮助，嗯，能帮我提炼想法
Yeah, writing is helpful for me. Um, both to kind of distill what I think.
今年夏天我写了一篇长文
But it's over the summer I wrote this like long piece,
就是那篇 “Future is for Everyone” 的文章，大约 15 页的文档
this like future is for everyone piece that was like a 15 page document
它帮助我梳理了自己在所有这些方面的理念
that kind of like was very helpful for me to distill my own philosophy on all these
围绕 AI 的各种重要社会议题。比如我认为什么是好的？什么……
different important social topics around AI. Like, what do I think is good? What?
与政府的互动应该是什么样？我们如何防范……
What should the interaction with governments be? How do we protect against, um,
人们担心的各种危害，对吧？
the different harms that people are worried about, right?
我们如何让数据中心对社区有好处，并且
How do we make it so data centers are good for communities and
这实际上会创造就业机会，而不是消灭它们？
that this actually creates jobs rather than eliminating them?
对。
Yeah.
并且我们能帮助保护国家安全，而且我们能，你知道，
And like that we can help protect national security and that we can, you know,
真正减轻，嗯，人们担心的任何危害，
really mitigate, um, any of the harms that people are worried about,
无论是黑客攻击，还是生物安全之类的事情。
whether that's like hacking or, or biosecurity type things.
是的，所以这就像是一件非常复杂的事情。
And yeah, so like it was just kind of like a very complex thing.
我花了很长时间，和很多人交流，修改了很多稿，
I took a long time, talked to a lot of people, went through a lot of drafts,
内部也有很多人，我们进行了辩论和交锋。
a lot of people internally, like kind of we debated and sparred about it.
但好吧，这对我来说是一个非常有益的过程。
But okay, it was very, it was a very helpful process for me.
最后，我们差不多有了这样的东西。就像是，好了，就是它，15页。
And then at the end, we kind of had this thing. It's like, all right, here it is, 15 pages.
这就是，我们所相信的。是的。
This is, like, what we believe. Yeah.
嗯，然后我把它提炼成一个一页纸的版本，并发表了
Um, and then I distilled that down to a one-page version that I published
作为一篇观点文章。对。嗯，我们做了一个简短的
as an op-ed. Yep. Um, we made a short.
关于它的视频，因为我觉得要触达很多人，
Video about it because I think to like reach a lot of people,
你通常甚至不想要这种理论性的论证。
you often don't even want like this like theoretical argument.
你只是想把它归结为，你的价值观是什么？
You just kind of wanna boil it down to like, what are your values?
比如，你相信什么？你如何传达这些？嗯，所以，我的意思是，
Like, what do you believe? How do you communicate that? Um, so, I mean,
所有这些都相当重要。
all that stuff is pretty important.
呃，但是的，我的意思是，这不像，你知道，
Uh, but yeah, I mean, it's, it's not like, you know,
就与公司或世界沟通而言，
in terms of communicating to the company or the world,
并不是一刀切的。
it's not like a one-size-fits-all.
我认为不同的时期需要不同的方式，在不同的节点，
I think different times call for different things and at different points,
某些群体要么本来就相信你正在做的事情，
like certain groups of people either just intrinsically believe in what you're doing
要么对此更加担忧。
or are more worried about it.
是的。需要带他们一起，或者需要额外努力解释为什么
Yeah. And need to kind of be brought along or need extra effort to explain why
这会有用。
that's gonna be useful.
所以，嗯，是的，我觉得无论怎样。
So, um, yeah, I think whatever.
我的意思是，我认为这是经营一家公司或做创始人的一部分，
I mean, I think this is part of like running a company or being a founder is like,
不是，你不会一遍又一遍地做同样的事情，
it's not, you don't just do the same thing over and over again
然后重复，你遇到的每种情况都有一点不同，有新的
and repeat like each situation you're in is like a little bit different with new
挑战，而且。
challenges that and.
嗯，我觉得这在一定程度上就是它有意思的地方。是的。
Um, and I think that that's partially what's interesting about it. Yeah.
嗯，我觉得对你来说也是，嗯，
Well, I think for you also, um,
似乎这种创始人心态不仅仅延伸到作为公司创始人之外，
it seems like this like founder mindset extends outside of just being a founder of
公司之外，无论是你的农场，还是学习一项技能。
the company, um, to whether it be your farm or learning a skill.
嗯，我就是喜欢构建东西。是的。好的。
Um, I just like building things. Yeah. Okay.
多跟我聊聊，构建东西对你来说是什么感觉？
Tell me more about like what does building things feel like to you?
嗯，我不知道。对我来说是什么感觉呢？
Um, I don't know. What does it feel like to me?
嗯，我想这有点像我的一种内在需求。就像，
Um, I guess it's kind of just like an intrinsic need that I have. Like,
我觉得我不是。
I feel like I'm not.
我觉得不同的人有不同的表达自我的需求。
I feel like different people have a need to express themselves in different ways.
比如如果你是作家，那我感觉他们可能会觉得，哦，
Like if you were a writer, then, like, I feel like they probably feel like, oh,
我需要写作，或者我觉得有些人感到需要，
I need to like write or I think some people feel the need to like,
被人喜欢之类的，然后他们就会，我不这样。
be liked or something and they go, I don't.
我只是，就是，我需要构建东西。
I just, like, I need to, like, build stuff.
我只是觉得如果我没有在发挥创造力、构建东西，我就会变得脾气暴躁。
I just think if I'm not, like, exercising my creativity and building stuff, I, I get grumpy.
你必须这样。这可不好。是的。你身边的每个人，
You have to. And that's not good. Yeah. Everyone around you,
我周围的人可不。
the people around me don't.
不希望我脾气暴躁。是的。是的。
Don't want me to be grumpy. Yeah. Yeah.
学习如何成为一个真正优秀的滑雪者，是同一种技能吗
Is it the same skill to like learn how to be like a really good skier
就像学习如何构建一个产品一样？
as it is to like, learn how to build a product.
嗯，是的。我认为学习新事物的过程非常相似。好的。嗯。
Um, yes. I think that the process for learning new things is pretty similar. Okay. Um.
在我的人生中，我尝试过一些我相当不擅长的事情。
In my life, I've tried to do some things that I was sort of quite bad at.
比如有一段时间，我一直很不擅长语言，你知道，这，
So at one point, like, so I was always very bad at languages and you know, that's,
这实际上就是我最开始学拉丁语的原因，因为我就是没法
that's like actually how I got into Latin in the first place is like I just couldn't
在课堂上说法语或西班牙语。
speak French or Spanish in class.
所以最后我想，好吧，拉丁语，那太好了。我不需要说它。
So finally I was like, alright, Latin, that's great. I don't need to speak it.
就像是，就像是它无法翻译。就像数学。
It's like, it's like it can't translate. It's like math.
对。嗯，后来当我开始经营公司的时候，
Yeah. Um, so then when I was, so then when I started running the company,
我开始做这些年度挑战。
I started doing these yearly challenges.
其中一项就是，学普通话吧。
And for one, I was like, let me learn Mandarin.
普通话真的是一门很难的语言，对吧？
Mandarin is like a really hard language, right?
我高中就学过。确实。是的，很棒但很难。
It's like I took it in high school. It's true. Yeah. Amazing, but hard.
对，对。
Yeah, yeah.
而且声调那部分，真的，怎么说呢，
And like, the tones thing, it's like, it's so, I mean,
有很多理由让我觉得学它很好。
there are all these reasons why I thought it was good.
比如 Priscilla 的外婆只会说普通话。
Like, I mean, Priscilla's grandma only speaks Mandarin.
所以如果我想和她交流，就必须学。
So if I wanted to communicate with her, I needed to learn it.
但最大的原因其实是它本身就是个挑战，嗯，
But, um, but, but the biggest part was actually just that it was a challenge and, um,
面对这类事情，你只能老老实实去做，
take all these things, you just kind of like show up
很多事情没办法靠聪明绕过。
and there's no way to outthink a bunch of these things.
我觉得你只能投入时间，
I think you just kind of like need to put in the time and you,
花时间去做，
you kind of spend your time doing it
它就会慢慢渗进你的大脑。
and it just kind of like seeps into your brain.
我觉得同样的道理适用于，不知道，
I think the same thing is true with like, I don't know,
学武术或者学开直升机之类的。
learning martial arts or like learning to fly a helicopter or something.
这些事情实际上，
It's like, these are things that they're actually, like,
很难纯靠理性去理解。
very hard to intellectualize.
我觉得做产品，有些部分更偏智力。
I think building products, I mean, parts of it are more intellectual.
写代码你可以用理论的方式去思考。
I think coding you can you can kind of think of in a theoretical way.
但做产品中那种直觉的部分，
But I think the the kind of intuitive part about building products.
只能通过反复练习来获得。
I think you only kind of do that by getting reps on that.
但问题就在于：你热爱什么，对吧？
But then the question is just like, what do you love, right?
因为我觉得有些人未必有和我一样的构建需求，
Because I think think some people don't necessarily have the same need to build
去构建东西。
things that I have.
大多数人都有某种需求。是的。
Most people have, have some need. Yeah.
关键是你要怎么找到自己的那个点，
And I think the key is like, how do you find what that is for yourself and then,
然后把时间投入进去，
like, go channel your, your time to, like,
去反复练习，在你想要的方向上做到出色。
go get the reps at that to become excellent at the thing that you like want to.
而且说实话，我觉得这不仅仅是“想要”。
And, and honestly, I think it goes beyond want.
它更像是某种，
I think it's sort of like this,
真正深层的心理需求或驱动力，推动你去做一件事。
like really like deep psychological need or drive to go do a thing.
我觉得把这种驱动力和对的事情对齐——
And I think like lining that up with like what?
并且给自己时间，让相关经验
And just kind of giving yourself the time to have the experience around
随着时间慢慢渗透。
that seep in over time.
对，我觉得这很特别。
Yeah. No, I think that's pretty special.
这基本上也是我养育孩子的方式，
I mean, this is, like, how I try to, like, raise my kids is basically, like,
让他们自己找到感兴趣的东西。
let them figure out what they kind of are interested in.
但他们会卡在某些地方。比如我一个女儿非常喜欢
But then they get hung up on something like one of my daughters is really into
做音乐，但她就是不喜欢——
making music, but she like could not.
她受不了上钢琴课，但后来我说，好吧，听着，
She could not stand taking piano lessons but was like, all right, look,
你不需要成为钢琴大师，但你要，
you don't need to become like a world expert at piano, but like you're gonna, like,
如果你想创作音乐，
if you want to be able to write music.
你会希望对一些东西有直觉的掌握，
Like you're gonna want to have an intuitive grasp of like some of the,
比如乐理和它的运作方式。
the music theory and, and how this works.
而且一旦学会弹钢琴，你学吉他会非常容易，
And once you learn how to, how to play piano, you're gonna be able to pick up guitar,
真的很容易。
like really easily.
对，没错。
Yeah, right.
所以我觉得，
And, um, and yeah, so I mean, I think that like just kind of, you know,
要有自律。小时候有父母帮助会好很多，
having the discipline, I mean, when you're a kid, having the parent probably helps.
但对成年人来说，
But, but like, but I think just like for grown-ups,
自律地坐下来，让那些东西通过反复练习渗入你的大脑，
just having the discipline to just kind of sit and let the stuff just seep into your,
这一点很关键。
your brain with the reps is I think a key part.
同意。
Agree.
我其实也觉得每个人都想构建点什么。
I also actually feel like everyone wants to build like,
我觉得尤其是 Z 世代，他们被贴上了坏名声，
I think especially like Gen Z does not get like there's a bad rap around Gen Z of
说他们缺乏主动性之类的。
like being kind of low agency and stuff.
但我真的觉得人们只是在寻找某种能点燃他们——
And I actually think that people are just like looking for something to ignite their
构建的能力。
ability to build.
嗯，你在哈佛时其实也聊了很多这个。我觉得那是……
Um, you talked about it actually a lot in your Harvard. I think that's.
对，对。嗯，是。
Yeah, yeah. Um, well, yeah.
不是，我觉得当我说“构建”时，
No, I think I guess when I say build,
我主要是在说这类产品，比如软件、
I'm talking a lot about like these kind of products, okay, right, like software,
硬件这类东西。
hardware, that kind of stuff.
但我同意。我觉得每个人都有某种创造驱动力。
But I agree. I think everyone has some sort of creative drive.
嗯，我觉得有些人，有些人性格里其他部分
Um, I guess some people have, some people have other parts of their personality
会压过这种驱动力。
that overpower that.
我的意思是，比如说，
I mean, it's like, for example, like, like, um,
我觉得对有些人来说就是服务他人，比如医学方面的驱动力。
I think for some people it's like just service, like the medical drive.
我觉得那些成为医生或护士的人，通常
I think like the type of people who become like a doctor or a nurse, I think often,
他们的主要驱动力就是，我真的很想
you know, just like their main drive is like, I just really want to, like,
帮助照顾别人。
help take care of people.
嗯，我明白。这很有意思。
Um, I know. It's interesting.
我听说过一个故事，
It's, um, I heard the story once
可能是 Priscilla 在医学院时，或者是在
where this might have actually been like from Priscilla at medical school or in the
医学院第一天，有人站起来问：你们
first day of medical school, someone got up and they, they asked like, do you.
有多少人小时候有过这样的记忆，
How many of you had a memory from when you were a kid of, like,
看到某个人时心里想，我真的很想照顾那个人。
seeing someone thinking like, I really just want to take care of that person.
然后所有人都举手了。我觉得对我来说，
And like every hand went up and I think it's like, it's like, for me,
我的版本是，我小时候有很多记忆是，
my version that was like, I have a lot of memories when I was a kid that's like,
我想要去构建这个东西，把它做得更好，对吧？
I want to go build this thing and make it better, right?
所以我觉得不是每个人都有同样类型的驱动力，
So I think like not everyone kind of has the same type of drive,
但我觉得每个人都有自己想做的事。
but I think everyone has stuff that they want to do.
我也同意，在以前那种技术条件下，
And I agree that like with the type of technology that we had, uh, before,
对很多人来说，光是起步就很难。
for a lot of people it's just hard to get started.
所以个人超级智能让我特别兴奋的一点是，
So one of the things that I'm really excited about with personal super intelligence
还有 Muse 以及这些智能体，它们带来的能力是，
and Muse and like all these AI agents is just like having the ability,
我想这是第一次人们真的能够很快地
I think for the first time for people to really be able to just like quickly get
开始动手，或者你只是有个大概的想法。
started or like you have some kind of like broad idea.
AI 可以先帮你画出草图，
And the AI can kind of start to sketch it out
然后你可以像雕刻一尊雕塑一样，把它慢慢打磨出来。
and then you can just like hone it in like you're kind of crafting a sculpture or something.
但你不需要，不需要一开始就什么都知道，
But you don't need to like, you don't need to know everything
不需要在开始之前就完全知道该怎么做。
before you get started about like how to go do the thing.
我觉得这真的很强大。
I think that's really powerful.
所以我觉得很多人会找到
So I think a lot of people are going to find things
他们想在这个世界上创造或去做的事情。
that they want to create or go do in the world.
完全同意。嗯，我觉得这会帮助人们获得更广泛的自主感。
Totally. Um, and I think that will help people feel like a much broader sense of agency.
好，聊聊生物和医学，这算是你在 Meta 之外的另一类项目。
Okay, on the bio note, medicine, that's like your other project outside of Meta.
目标是解决所有疾病。对。嗯，我很好奇，第一，我们离这个目标有多近？
It's to solve all diseases. Yeah. Um, I'm curious, number one, how close are we?
第二……现在近了很多。对。你现实来看觉得有多近？
And then No. 2. A lot closer now. Yeah. How close, like, do you think realistically?
嗯，最初我们启动这个项目时，
Well, I mean, originally when we started it,
目标是在本世纪末帮助科学界治愈所有疾病。
the goal was to help the scientific community cure all diseases by the end of the century.
所以我们的目标从来不是自己去做成这件事。
So our goal, we were never going to do it ourselves.
我们的观点、我们的理论基本是：所有重大科学进步
Our view is, like, our theory is basically all major scientific advances
之前都先出现一种能测量和理解某些事物的新工具。
have been preceded by a new tool to be able to measure and understand something.
所以，就像有了显微镜，然后你才了解细菌，对吧？
So, you know, it's like you got the microscope, then you understood bacteria, right?
有了望远镜，帮助我们理解世界上正在发生的很多事情。
You got a telescope that helped us understand a lot about what's going on in the world.
嗯，在宇宙中。
Um, in the universe.
嗯，其中一些东西还成了平台，
Um, some of these things are platforms too,
比如，第一个发明疫苗的人。
like you had the first person who created a vaccine.
现在人们就能针对不同疾病创造出很多疗法。对。嗯，
Now like people can create a lot of different cures for things. Yeah. Um,
但很多
but a lot of the.
科学资助的历史运作方式是，
The way that science funding has worked historically is,
把资金非常分散地投给个人去做独立探索。
is kind of very widely dispersing funding for people to do individual exploration.
但对这些大型工具的资金投入一直没那么多。
But there hasn't been that much funding for these big tools.
嗯，这基本上就是我们在 Biohub 想做的事：设计一些
And, um, that's basically what we're trying to do with Biohub is design a few of
新的工具，给人们观察生物学的新方式
these new tools that give people new ways of seeing biology
希望能帮助科学界加速进步。
that can hopefully help the scientific community just accelerate progress.
之前我们觉得，也许到本世纪末，
So before we thought, you know, maybe by the end of the century,
我们刚开始做的时候，我觉得那可能性很大，
I thought that that was like pretty likely when we got started,
当时这观点还很有争议。
it was pretty controversial.
我觉得很多生物学家认为那不太可能。
I think a lot of the biologists thought that that was unlikely.
现在我觉得这个时间线太长了。
Now I think it's like way too long.
我认为随着 AI 的进步，以及我们现在做的一些工作，
I think with the progress in AI and some of the stuff that we're working on now,
我们正在构建一个完整的虚拟细胞模型，基本上就是，
we're building this whole virtual cell model where basically, like,
不必再在真实的活细胞上做实验。
instead of having to experiment on, like, actual physical living cells.
你基本上可以有一个 AI 模型来模拟蛋白质，
You basically can have an AI model that simulates the proteins,
然后模拟一个细胞，之后最终也许能模拟，
then simulates a cell, then after that, eventually simulating like maybe, you know,
一个虚拟免疫系统，或者整个生物体，甚至整个人。
a virtual immune system or a whole organism or whole person.
这会让人们能进行大量不同的实验，并且，
It's, um, that's just gonna let people run so many different experiments and, like,
模拟不同情况下会发生什么。
simulate what happens in different situations.
如果给某个人吃这种药，会发生什么？
If you give someone this medicine, what types of things happen?
这会非常强大。所以，我不确定。
Um, that's gonna be really powerful. So, yeah, I don't know.
我不想给这个定一个具体的年限，但。
I don't wanna put like an exact number of years on this, but.
我猜它会，
I would guess it's gonna be like,
我觉得会比本世纪末快得多。
it's gonna be much sooner I think than by the end of the century.
你觉得用“解决所有疾病”而不是“永生”，是不是有意为之？
And do you think 'solve all diseases' feels very intentional over, like, 'live forever'?
永生是可能的吗？
Is live forever a possibility?
嗯，这不完全是我的领域。
Well, that's not as much my field.
我觉得当然有可能。
I think, certainly.
嗯，我觉得这是两种不太一样的事情。我觉得永生更多是……
Well, I think that there are two kind of different things. I think live forever is...
更多是关于延长。
More about extending.
我觉得即使你不生病，到某个时候，人类身体仍然有，
I think even if you didn't get sick, I think at some point the human body has,
它目前的自然寿命上限，对吧。
has its current natural life expectancy, okay.
所以我认为这是一个需要单独研究的问题。
So I think it's a separate problem to work on that.
有些人会把那看作一种疾病。
Some people would view that as a disease.
嗯，对，我觉得这么看也合理。
Um, yeah, like, and I think, yeah, that's a reasonable way to view it.
但我认为人们也需要去研究，
But I think people also need to work on, like,
治愈和预防那些疾病——即使你
curing and preventing the diseases that will get you even if you kind of get
把寿命问题解决了，它们仍会找上你。
that worked out.
所以这就是我们选择去解决的那部分问题。
Yeah, so that's the part of the problem that we've chosen to work on.
嗯，而且这也不是说你永远不会得感冒之类的。
Um, and again, it's not that like you will never get a cold or something.
我觉得有些东西是，你希望能做到——我们称之为治愈、
I think like some of the stuff is that you want to be able to, we call it cure,
预防或管理。
prevent or manage.
对。有些病，你得了之后可以完全治愈。
Yeah, right. So some things, like, you get it, you can fully cure it.
有些病，我认为我们将能够有某种方法，
Some things I think we're going to be able to have something
让你永远不会得。
that can prevent you from ever getting it.
还有一些，我觉得就算你生病了，
And some of these, I think you'll just be able to, like, maybe you, you, you get sick,
但那个东西本来会造成真正的伤害，甚至致命。
but the thing would have caused, you know, like real damage or would have killed you.
但即使它不会杀死你，如果可能造成真正伤害，
But even if it wasn't gonna kill you, if it might cause real damage,
现在你也可以把它控制住。
but now you can just kind of manage it.
它会变成一种持续的状态，
It's this ongoing thing where it's, um, it's just like, you know,
基本不会影响你的生活质量。
doesn't really get in the way of your quality of life.
所以我觉得这些都会是重要组成部分，
So I think all of those will be kind of important parts of, of,
是最终图景的重要组成部分。
of what this looks like.
但人类身体，就像是，
But the human body, and it's like the,
目标是让它保持平衡，对吧？
the goal is to keep it in equilibrium, right?
所以并不是说我们永远不会遇到病原体之类的。
So it's not that we're like never gonna encounter a pathogen or something.
我只是认为在某个时间点，我们将能够
It's like we just, I just think that at some point in time we're gonna be able to
治愈、预防和管理所有疾病。
cure, prevent and manage all diseases.
是的，太令人兴奋了，因为我觉得 AI 就像是催化剂，
Yeah, it's so exciting 'cause I think that AI has like been this catalyst in
推动了许多这样的突破。
so many different breakthroughs like that.
然后还有个人智能这个方面。
And then you have the personal intelligence aspect.
嗯，你现在最常思考什么？
Um, what are you thinking about most frequently right now?
在做这些工作时，你脑中最常出现的想法是什么？
Like, as you're working on this, what's, like, the most common thought in your head?
嗯，这大概每周都会变，你知道，
Um, well, that probably changes week to week, you know, I mean,
现在非常专注于 Muse。
Right now, very focused on Muse.
而且当你发布东西时总是很令人兴奋。你快速行动，你努力去……
And it's always just very exciting when you launch something. You move quickly, you try to.
你要接触世界。
You make contact with the world.
你了解人们的想法，然后搞清楚接下来需要做什么。
You learn what people think and then you figure out what you need to go work on next.
所以我们现在正处于一个阶段：我们在获取大量关于……
So we're just in a phase now where we're getting a lot of information about what
人们想要什么的信息，很多好消息是大家很喜欢它。
people want, a lot of the good news is that people love it.
所以我们在努力把它带给尽可能多的人。
So we're working to just kind of get it to as many people as possible.
模型方面还有很多工作要做，对吧？
There's a lot of work on the models, right?
Muse Spark 模型已经取得了很大进展。
The Muse Spark models have made a lot of progress.
我对此非常自豪。是的，我们还想继续推进。
I'm really proud of that. Yeah, we still want to keep pushing that.
我们想推动前沿，而且，
We want to push the frontier and like,
而且我们至少想拥有世界领先的模型。
and we would like to have the world's leading models at least.
你们如何做到这一点？
How do you get there?
需要哪些突破？
What breakthroughs are needed?
嗯，研究这件事的特点是，你并不一定一开始就知道。
Well, the thing about research is you don't necessarily know upfront.
我的意思是，我们大致感觉到我们的团队正在取得一些突破。
I mean, we have a sense of like some breakthroughs that we think our folks are making.
所以有很多东西让我很兴奋，
So there's a bunch of stuff that I'm excited about,
但过去一年里，很多工作实际上只是在扩展基础设施。
but a lot of it over the last year has actually just been scaling the infrastructure.
你知道，如果回到一年半以前，
You know, if you went back like a year and a half ago,
我想更多人可能会说，
I think that more people probably would have said
为了实现超级智能，
that in order to get to super intelligence,
你需要一些根本性的架构突破，对吧？
you would need some fundamental architecture breakthroughs, okay?
而我现在并不确定这一点是否仍然成立。我觉得我们已经差不多有了。
And I'm not actually sure that that's true at this point. I think we kind of have.
对配方是什么有了感觉，而且
A sense of what the recipe is and
如果你能建一个足够大的超级计算机集群，
if you could just build a big enough supercomputer cluster,
那么我觉得你可以靠算力硬推达成目标。
then I think you can brute force it and get there.
有意思。所以我的意思是，比如我们正在建这个，你知道，
Interesting. So I mean, like we are building this, you know,
俄亥俄州的吉瓦级集群。
gigawatt-plus cluster in Ohio.
它基本上已经上线了。我们在用它训练下一代模型。
It's basically online. We're using that to train our next generation of models.
我认为那些模型会很出色。然后我们还在建 5 吉瓦集群，
I think that those models will be great. Then we're building the 5 gigawatt cluster,
嗯，在路易斯安那州。
um, in Louisiana.
那会很棒。是的。
So that's gonna be awesome. Yeah.
嗯，而且我猜，当你拥有一个多吉瓦集群用于
Um, and yeah, I would guess that by the time you have a multi gigawatt cluster doing
训练时，你基本上就会拥有某种东西，
training, you're basically gonna have something
它接近你随便怎么称呼的东西，AGI，你知道，
that approximates whatever you want to call it, AGI, you know,
我认为那是超越这一层的超级智能。
I think super intelligence beyond that.
哇。嗯，但这并不意味着这是最好的方式。
Wow. Um, but that doesn't mean it's the best way to do it.
嗯，你知道，我的意思是，我觉得人类大脑。
Um, you know, I mean I think that the human brain.
运行功率大约是 10 瓦。对吧。
Runs on about 10 Watts. Yeah, right.
所以我觉得，也许我们正在构建的这些计算系统，
So I think like maybe these computational systems that we're building are,
可以说是效率大约比那低一百万倍。
call it, on the order of a million times less efficient than that.
所以我确实认为会有架构上的改进，
So I do think that there are going to be architecture improvements
有人能找到。
that someone can find.
是的，我们当然也在努力做这件事，因为
Yeah, and we're certainly working on doing that because
如果你把拥有如此巨大的算力
if you combine both having this huge amount of compute
和架构改进结合起来，我认为你才真正能构建出
and the architecture improvement that I think you'll really build something
领先于整个领域的东西。
that is ahead of the rest of the field.
但在现阶段，我认为扩展算力能带我们走很远。
But at this point I think the scaling can take us pretty far.
是的，挺有意思，因为扩展算力也感觉是最有把握的保证。
Yeah, it's interesting 'cause it also feels like scaling is the easiest guarantee.
比如研究，你必须真的希望出现重大突破，
Like with research, you have to, like, really hope that there's a big breakthrough,
但扩展算力可以很快就扩大规模。
but scaling could just really scale up quickly.
我知道这就是为什么大公司都在朝这个方向投入，
I know that's why the bigger companies are going for it
因为可能存在便宜得多的方式来做这件事，
because it may be that there is a much cheaper way to do it,
但我们还不知道。
but we don't know that yet.
是的，是的。
Yeah, yeah.
但这件事太有价值了，值得在世界上创造出来，如果你知道
But like this is such a valuable thing to create in the world that if you know
有相当高的概率能做成它，
that there's a pretty high probability chance of doing it,
即便需要花费数千亿美元去做，它仍然
even if it's going to cost many hundreds of billions of dollars to go do it is still
值得去做。
worth it to go do that.
为了确保万一你没有发现某些
To make sure that if in the off event you do not also discover some of the
本可以用低得多的成本实现这件事的突破。
breakthroughs that would have enabled it for, for a lot less.
你仍然有明确的机会去做到。
You still have a clear shot to do that.
当然，如果你真的发现了它，那只会变得更好，这很棒。
And then, of course, if you do discover it, then it just gets even better, which is great.
所以我觉得这部分，
So I kind of think that part of it,
我不想说它已经解决了，因为现实是，
I don't want to call it solved because the reality is,
在扩展基础设施来实现这一点时，会有全新的工程挑战。
is that there are novel engineering challenges in scaling up the infrastructure to do that.
而且在训练模型的每个阶段，
And at each level of training the models,
你都会遇到新的奇怪问题，必须调试并让它正常运行。
you encounter new weird things that you have to debug and get to work well.
所以我觉得，这大概就是研究工作的方式。
So I think that's kind of just sort of the way
研究就是这样运作的。
that the research works.
它就是这样迭代的。
It's sort of iterative like that.
可能现在最重要的事情之一
Probably one of the most important things
就是专注 alignment（对齐），
that we need to do now is focus on alignment and,
以及让模型变得可信。
and kind of making the models trustworthy.
我觉得这对……会非常重要。
And I think that this is going to be really important for.
行业里有这么一场争论，就是，
And there's this whole debate in the industry which is like, yeah, is this, like,
各个实验室会自然而然地重视它吗？
are the labs gonna naturally focus on it?
我的看法是，会的。
And my view is like, yeah, I mean,
实验室自然会重视，因为，
the labs should naturally focus on it because like,
我不知道有多少人会愿意用 Muse 智能体，
I don't know how many people are gonna wanna use the Muse agent
如果你让它做一件事，它却……
if you tell it to do something and it, like.
做了与你要求相反的事，对吧？
Does the opposite of what you asked it to do, right?
它需要……我们需要确保我们构建的产品和模型
It needs to, like, we need to make sure that the products and the models
不仅能理解
that we build understand not only.
你具体要求了什么，
Like specifically what you asked,
还能理解背后的意图和你的价值观，这样它们就不会去做
but the intent behind it and your values, that way they don't go do the thing
你不希望的方式，或造成
that you wanted in a way that you were unhappy with or cause some,
你不想要的负面影响。
like negative effect that you wouldn't have wanted.
所以它需要在相当深的层次上理解你，这就是对齐。
Um, so it needs to understand at a pretty deep level and that's kind of alignment.
所以我的看法是，为了让 Muse 成功，
And so my view is like, in order for Muse to be successful
并触及十亿甚至数十亿人，
and reach a billion or billions of people,
我们某种程度上必须解决对齐问题，或者说，
we sort of are going to have to solve alignment or solve, I mean,
基本上要在这方面取得非常大的进展。
it's basically like make very good progress on that.
这是由用户来实现吗？
Does it happen by the user?
比如用户说“嘿，这不是我让你做的”，还是由你们
Being like, hey, that is not what I wanted you to do or does it happen by you guys
在后端自己发现？
in the back end just realizing.
我觉得是两者结合。
I think it's a combination of both.
我的意思是，我们看到的情况是，
I mean, I think what we're seeing, I mean,
我们确实会从用户那里得到反馈，但，
there's definitely feedback that we get from, from people, but.
我也认为，越来越多的实验室看到的是，
I also think that increasingly what the labs are seeing is
你必须在训练过程中就做对齐，
that you need to do alignment as you're training it
因为模型已经聪明到，如果你不这样做，
because the models are getting smart enough that if you don't, I mean,
很多安全和安保事件
a lot of the safety and security incidents
我们在其他实验室看到的，基本都发生在训练期间，
that we're seeing at the other labs are basically during training,
而不是在模型部署给用户使用之后。
not after they've deployed the model for people to use. So.
很多情况是，为了训练出
A lot of this is, okay, in order to be able to train something
这种智力水平的东西，你需要制定一套
that is of this level of intelligence, you need to develop a, like,
非常好的训练方案。
very good curriculum for it.
而且，就像父母一样，你需要设定明确的边界，这样
And, you know, like a parent, you need to set firm boundaries so that way
如果它做错了什么，它就会学到：不，
if it does something that is wrong, you kind of, it learns that, that is like, no,
我是想让你真正解决这个编程问题。
I wanted you to actually solve this coding problem.
我不想让你通过更改某些系统配置来获得奖励。
I didn't want you to like get the reward by changing some system configuration.
对，比如改某个值或绕过它。
Yeah, that, like, change some value or hacking around it.
我是想让你真正经历
I wanted you to actually like go through the, the, the,
解决问题的过程，这样你才能学会方法。
the work to solve the problems that you'd learn the method of doing that.
这就是训练的意义。对。
I mean, that's the point of training. Yeah.
所以，这部分也涉及良好的安全性，
So, um, yeah, so part of that is just about kind of having good security,
建立明确而坚定的边界。
establishing good firm boundaries.
而且，我觉得所有这些都是行业自然要做的事，
Um, and yeah, I mean, I think all this stuff is just natural stuff
我们也在上面花了很多时间。
that the industry is gonna have to do, um, that we're spending a lot of time on.
而且，每天都不一样。
And, um, yeah, that's, it's, you know, every day is different.
因为你之前也提到 AI 安全方面，嗯。
Well, 'cause I think you also said that with the AI safety stuff, um,
我感觉这件事在最近两周真的到了爆发点。
like I feel like it's kind of come to a head in the last two weeks,
虽然其实并没有哪一个具体时刻让它发生。
even though there hasn't been like actually a moment that has made that happen.
但听起来你的看法是，你们其实把这个模型多留了几个月
But it sounded like your take was we actually held this model for a few extra months
然后只是在内部完成了训练。
and we just did the training internally.
对，我的意思是，对于 Muse，我们知道这个产品必须非常注重隐私和安全。
Yeah, I mean, for Muse, we knew that the product needed to be very private and secure.
所以基本上，我们已经有一个更早版本的模型。
So we basically, we had an earlier version of the model.
我们觉得可以再训练一些，
We thought that we could train in some,
一些关于审慎行事的行为，就像我们之前聊到的。
some more behavior around discretion like we talked about.
所以我们花了时间去做这件事。
So we, we took the time to do that.
另外还有很多工作是让虚拟机，
There's also a bunch of stuff about making the virtual machine,
也就是我们给每个 Muse 智能体提供的那台电脑更安全。
the computer that we give to each Muse agent more secure.
所以我们多花了几个月来做这些。
So we took a few extra months to do that.
嗯，但我的意思是，我也不确定。我觉得，你知道，当其他实验室……
Um, but I mean, I don't know. I think, you know, when, when other labs.
其他实验室经常说，哦，我们正在，像是，
Other labs have often talked about, oh, we're, like,
承受很多痛苦来放慢进度。
taking a bunch of pain in order to slow stuff down.
我觉得，这对 Meta 和……
Like, my view is it's like, that was the right thing for both Meta
以及将来会使用 Muse 的人来说，都是正确的做法。
and for the people who are gonna use Muse.
就像，你知道，我们想把产品做好，
Like, if, you know, it's like, we wanna make the product good,
如果产品不够好，那对用户也不好，
and if the product isn't good, then it's not good for people
对我们也不好，对吧？
and it's also not good for us, right?
我们不想推出一个东西，结果它，你知道，
It's like, we don't wanna put something out and have it be, you know,
留下糟糕的第一印象，然后大家就不太愿意去用了。
a bad first impression and then people aren't excited to go use it.
所以，嗯，我也说不好。
So, um, so I don't know.
我有点觉得，我自己的看法是，
I kind of think, I mean my own view on this is that I think
所有实验室都会有相当强的内在动力把这件事做好。
that all the labs are gonna have a pretty strong intrinsic incentive to get this right.
完全同意。对，感觉只要你把激励对齐到让它变得非常……
Totally. Yeah, it feels like if you just align the incentives to it being incredibly
有价值且安全，那就……
valuable and safe, and that's.
对，完全同意，完全同意。嗯，非常感谢你抽出时间。是的，
Yeah, totally, totally. Well, thank you so much for your time. Yeah,
恭喜你们迎来这么重要的一周。谢谢。谢谢。太棒了。
congrats on a huge week. Thank you. Thank you. Awesome.